<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Vivek Nallur</title>
    <link>http://viveknallur.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Vivek Nallur</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright &amp;#169; by Vivek Nallur</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 02 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://viveknallur.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Slides for CS3012</title>
      <link>http://viveknallur.github.io/teaching/slides/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://viveknallur.github.io/teaching/slides/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Slides from the lectures for the CS 3012 course on Software Engineering can be
found here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;slides:90014a872bdadc29d38e0ddafb91b9e9&#34;&gt;Slides&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://viveknallur.github.io/slides/01-introduction.pdf&#34;&gt;Introduction to the Module&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CS3012 - Software Engineering</title>
      <link>http://viveknallur.github.io/teaching/cs3012/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://viveknallur.github.io/teaching/cs3012/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;This is the landing page for the CS 3012 course on Software Engineering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here you can find announcements regarding the course, and other miscellaneous
information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;announcements:e3569ea0094b2f25a013d21134dc31b1&#34;&gt;Announcements&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The module repository is now live and all students &lt;strong&gt;must&lt;/strong&gt; request access to
be able to submit assignments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Urban Infrastructure and Democracy</title>
      <link>http://viveknallur.github.io/smartcities/city-systems-report/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://viveknallur.github.io/smartcities/city-systems-report/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The term &lt;em&gt;smart cities&lt;/em&gt; gets a lot of play in the tech press and there are many companies that present solutions in this space. But the root cause of the problem isn&amp;rsquo;t
the lack of technology. Rather, it is pressure of population and the scarcity of resources in urban agglomerations, in a future that seems almost as inevitable as climate change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given this dystopian near-future, sustainability is the most important aspect that a wannabe smart city should focus on. And sustainability requires active and enthusiastic
participation from citizens. Instead of focussing on how many objects in a city are &lt;em&gt;connected&lt;/em&gt;, the emphasis should be on disseminating information and knowledge (which is quite a different concept) to
citizens, so that they can participate fruitfully in how their city and life is governed. In my opinion, this is the smartest thing a smart-city could do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, the Indian government announced an &lt;a href=&#34;http://smartcities.gov.in/&#34;&gt;urban renewal and infrastructural development mission&lt;/a&gt; that envisages the creation of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.makeinindia.com/article/-/v/internet-of-things&#34;&gt;100 smart cities&lt;/a&gt;
as a part of a larger agenda of creating an industrial corridor between the existing mega-cities of Delhi, Mumbai, Chennai, and Kolkata. While the mission may be ambitious (and laudable)
in terms of providing access to world-class infrastructure, to a large proportion of the population, it would be foolish to expect growth to be smooth and sustainable without explicit
steps taken to ensure that this happens. Depending on city growth to somehow organically result in an increase in the quality of life is a recipe for disaster. Anyone who has
navigated Bangalore traffic knows that unless urban infrastructural problems (and solutions) are measured and scrutinized regularly in an objective manner, there is no hope
of improvement in city life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.janaagraha.org/about-us/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Janaagraha Centre for Citizenship and Democracy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; attempts to provide the first part of the jigsaw, in this regard.
Their &lt;a href=&#34;http://janaagraha.org/reports/ASICS-2015.pdf&#34;&gt;annual survey on city-systems&lt;/a&gt; is a data-rich report with problem evaluation and measurement. Anyone interested
in a bird&amp;rsquo;s eye view of problems, across 21 Indian cities  should take a look. London and New York are included as benchmarks.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Smoothest Streets in Dublin</title>
      <link>http://viveknallur.github.io/smarthopper/least_bumpy_ride/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://viveknallur.github.io/smarthopper/least_bumpy_ride/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h4 id=&#34;least-bumpy-routing:2cd36ad9af90a975251feeaeed6d527a&#34;&gt;Least Bumpy Routing&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://viveknallur.github.io/smarthopper/introduction&#34;&gt;SmartHopper&lt;/a&gt; extended to use road smoothness data provided by cyclists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the aims of SmartHopper is to be able to accept any spatial sensor data provided by citizens, and turn it into
useful information. One of our Masters&amp;rsquo; students is an avid cyclist, and he wrote an app that collected smoothness data
from sensors attached to bikes. He then asked his friends to attach sensors and simply use it during their daily rides
through the city. We were able to turn this road-by-road smoothness data into a heatmap and routing information with
minimal effort (took us about 2-3 person days).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take a look at the routing that&amp;rsquo;s now made possible, with SmartHopper
&lt;img src=&#34;http://viveknallur.github.io/images/smarthopper/Least_Bumpy_800x600.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Smoothest Cycling Route Through Dublin&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice, that in the visualization, the user can opt to see different layers of road smoothness. And also, SmartHopper simply took
this information, and used it for providing the smoothest (or rather, &amp;ldquo;least bumpy&amp;rdquo;) route.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What else can you imagine SmartHopper being extended for?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SEAMS&#39;16 Paper Accepted</title>
      <link>http://viveknallur.github.io/posts/seams-acceptance/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://viveknallur.github.io/posts/seams-acceptance/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our paper entitled &lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;Clonal Plasticity: A Method for Decentralized Adaptation
in Multi-Agent Systems&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt; accepted at &lt;a href=&#34;http://seams2016.jgreen.de/&#34;&gt;SEAMS&amp;rsquo;2016&lt;/a&gt;
Yaay!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll put up a pre-print copy of the paper in the &lt;em&gt;research&lt;/em&gt; section of the site. In the meantime, if you just can&amp;rsquo;t wait, send me an email.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>AAMAS&#39;16 Paper Accepted</title>
      <link>http://viveknallur.github.io/posts/aamas-acceptance/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://viveknallur.github.io/posts/aamas-acceptance/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our paper entitled &lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;Algorithm-Diversity: A Mechanism for Distributive Justice in a Socio-Technical MAS&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt; accepted at &lt;a href=&#34;http://sis.smu.edu.sg/aamas2016&#34;&gt;AAMAS&amp;rsquo;2016&lt;/a&gt;
Yaay!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll put up a pre-print copy of the paper in the &lt;em&gt;research&lt;/em&gt; section of the site. In the meantime, if you just can&amp;rsquo;t wait, send me an email.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Successful Thesis Defense!</title>
      <link>http://viveknallur.github.io/posts/eamonn-passes/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://viveknallur.github.io/posts/eamonn-passes/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h5 id=&#34;eamonn-o-toole-passes-his-viva-on-decentralized-emergence-detection-with-flying-colours:d098cef219f9391405a424ae6f194f17&#34;&gt;Eamonn O&amp;rsquo;Toole passes his viva on decentralized emergence detection with flying colours!&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eamonn successfully defended his thesis (entitled &amp;ldquo;Decentralized Detection of Emergence in Complex Adaptive Systems&amp;rdquo;) on 15-Jan-2016. Way to go, soon-to-be Dr. Eamonn! Very well done!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>FutureCities on YouTube!</title>
      <link>http://viveknallur.github.io/posts/futurecities-youtube/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://viveknallur.github.io/posts/futurecities-youtube/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;FutureCities now has a Youtube! channel&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The FutureCities centre now has a Youtube! channel, so it&amp;rsquo;s easier to find all
of our work (when you&amp;rsquo;re not looking up our papers ;))&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC9odOg7SQMug4mQGzdJJehg&#34;&gt;FutureCities Youtube Channel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thesis Submission!</title>
      <link>http://viveknallur.github.io/posts/eamonn-submits/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://viveknallur.github.io/posts/eamonn-submits/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h5 id=&#34;eamonn-o-toole-submits-his-thesis-on-decentralized-emergence-detection:dee999b9b5019ee00d8b9e52e357b2eb&#34;&gt;Eamonn O&amp;rsquo;Toole submits his thesis on decentralized emergence detection!&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eamonn has just submitted his thesis entitled &amp;ldquo;Decentralized Detection of Emergence in Complex Adaptive Systems&amp;rdquo;. Way to go, Eamonn! Very well done! Of course, it&amp;rsquo;s really special to me since he&amp;rsquo;s my first PhD student mentee. It&amp;rsquo;s been a pleasure discussing philosophies, ideas, problems and solution concepts with you, mate. Hope you go far!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thesis looks at the problem of detecting emergence in a large-scale complex adaptive systems, where each part could potentially be adapting independently. Given the large-scale and decentralized nature of such systems, the big questions are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Is it possible to detect emergence in a decentralized fashion?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;How do you know which variables are interesting, given that the environment
and the components themselves, change dynamically?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For answers to these questions (and more), read his thesis! (We&amp;rsquo;ve also submitted a paper to TAAS. Fingers crossed!).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reproducible Results in Software Engineering</title>
      <link>http://viveknallur.github.io/research/reproducible_research/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://viveknallur.github.io/research/reproducible_research/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the central problem we face in all of computer science is how we are
to get to the situation where we build on top of the work of others rather
than redoing so much of it in a trivially different way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ndash; Richard Hamming (From Turing Award lecture(1968))
&lt;em&gt;Journal of the ACM (Jan 1969), 16, No. 1, 10.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;reproducing-and-sharing-results-of-experiments-in-software-engineering:0a02261f8657866700056ef61d86ade2&#34;&gt;Reproducing and Sharing Results of Experiments in Software Engineering&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Richard Hamming&amp;rsquo;s statement has perhaps never been as true, as it is true today. There are literally hundreds of conferences, with tens of thousands of papers published every year. Surely, going by the volume of output, we should be in a much better position with regard to the big problems, than we are at the moment. Of course, there are some problems that are genuinely hard, but even so, a whole lot of effort is expended in trying to do something trivially better or trivially different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of the problem is that, at least in computer science, there&amp;rsquo;s no value accorded to repeating and verifying experiments. Due to the proliferation of platforms, libraries, languages, the amount of effort involved in reproducing someone else&amp;rsquo;s experiment is so huge that the average researcher doesn&amp;rsquo;t attempt it. If one is unable to reproduce a result, so what? It must be because the environment wasn&amp;rsquo;t just right, or the data-structure wasn&amp;rsquo;t the same as the one in the paper. Or reproducer&amp;rsquo;s code is wrong (even more insidiously, &amp;ldquo;has a bug&amp;rdquo;). The net result is that not many results are reproduced, which of course, then leads to a situation, where published papers have non-reproduceable results! This state of affairs would be unacceptable in any other science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Software Engineering has yet to figure out how to document and preserve forever and ever, the ideas/decisions/assumptions behind a big piece of code, we have reached a point where it is possible to checkpoint a piece of working code and make it available economically to anyone who wants it. Virtual Machines, while cool and dandy, are terribly big and difficult to share. Docker containers, though, in  my opinion, hit a sweet spot where, for certain kinds of code and libraries, the exact configuration and environment can be captured and shared with the world. Thanks to the Docker hub, we can also be reasonably sure that it (the code) won&amp;rsquo;t go away, as soon as researcher moves institutions (To my great mortification and embarrassment, all of my code and data vanished from my PhD student website, soon after I graduated. Which meant that reproducing (and building upon) my TSE paper results was next to impossible).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;docker-hub-address:0a02261f8657866700056ef61d86ade2&#34;&gt;Docker Hub Address&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having learnt my lesson, I&amp;rsquo;m going to put up all of  my paper submissions&amp;rsquo; code
up on Docker Hub in a docker container. So, at the very least, folks can reproduce my results, if not build on it. I&amp;rsquo;m also trying to convince my colleagues to do the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://hub.docker.com/r/viveknallur/&#34;&gt;Vivek Nallur&amp;rsquo;s Docker Hub Repo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Future Cities</title>
      <link>http://viveknallur.github.io/smartcities/futurecities/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://viveknallur.github.io/smartcities/futurecities/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tcd.ie/futurecities/&#34;&gt;Future cities research centre&lt;/a&gt; is a multi-disciplinary centre at Trinity College Dublin. Its mission is to
conduct holistic research into all aspects of a smart and sustainable city, and not just view a city as a agglomeration of sensors and people.  It connects
researchers across Trinity, and brings to bear multiple perspectives on the pressing problems of urban living. Typical smart city projects tend to concentrate
on leveraging sensors and the much-vaunted &lt;em&gt;Internet of Things&lt;/em&gt;, to create technical solutions to human problems. We believe that while technology can and should
play an important enabling role in a sustainable future, ultimately the citizens must take responsibility for their city. We investigate projects that can bring
to bear legal policy, urban planning, economic incentives, and educational awareness to nudge citizens towards a healthier and sustainable future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;active-areas-of-research:0902b81ceffb0826a9dc92843526137b&#34;&gt;Active Areas of Research&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We work on areas such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tcd.ie/futurecities/research/mobility/&#34;&gt;Smart Mobility&lt;/a&gt;: Future Cities&amp;rsquo; Mobility research strand focuses on addressing the effects of increasing road usage including delay, unpredictable journey times, exessive pollution, and driver frustration as well as to improve road safety.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tcd.ie/futurecities/research/energy/&#34;&gt;Energy Management&lt;/a&gt;: The Future Cities’ Energy research strand focuses on technology development of platforms that enable services for urban energy management. The approaches investigated include forecasting energy demand, improving energy efficiency within the built environment and integrating renewable energy sources into the electrical grid.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tcd.ie/futurecities/research/pollution/&#34;&gt;Pollution&lt;/a&gt;: The Future Cities’ Pollution research strand looks at improving methodologies for monitoring levels of urban pollution.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tcd.ie/futurecities/research/citizen-engagement/&#34;&gt;Citizen Engagement&lt;/a&gt;: This research strands addresses how citizens can be integrated early in the research pipeline, to ensure that practical considerations are taken into account, highlighting potential negative impact on society (e.g., through weakened privacy and security) and effectively to co-design potential futures.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tcd.ie/futurecities/research/urban-scale-data/&#34;&gt;Urban-Scale Data&lt;/a&gt;: This research strand addresses middleware and communications architectures to allow high volumes of data from public, business-owned and user-contributed sensors to be gathered and exploited by smart cities. This area merges wireless sensor networks, vehicular sensor networks, and participatory sensing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;interested:0902b81ceffb0826a9dc92843526137b&#34;&gt;Interested?&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tcd.ie/futurecities/contact/&#34;&gt;Talk to us&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Thinking Primate</title>
      <link>http://viveknallur.github.io/contact/thinking-ape/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://viveknallur.github.io/contact/thinking-ape/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Some folks have asked (maybe more have silently wondered) why the landing page features an ape. Especially since, as an academic, the general thrust
of a website is to promote a &amp;lsquo;respectable&amp;rsquo; image of the owner. I suppose, in some weird way, it&amp;rsquo;s a rebellion against the carefully manufactured  image that
most computer scientists / academics put out into the world (be it of a hacker, thinker, cool-dude, name-your-stereotype). Having an ape be the first impression leads to
a distortion of what people expect from an academic&amp;rsquo;s site. It lets visitors take me a little less seriously, and reminds me that everything is ephemeral (impressions, papers, philosophies).
It&amp;rsquo;s better to live life, than to think about living it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, in a way, it pays homage to my evolutionary grand-parents. It always pays to know your roots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides, my wife thinks the resemblance is quite striking :)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Site Design</title>
      <link>http://viveknallur.github.io/contact/site/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 May 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://viveknallur.github.io/contact/site/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, for some reason, during my academic and professional journey through computer science,
I&amp;rsquo;ve never picked up website design/technologies. While I was in school, HTML 3.x was still
the standard (yes, I&amp;rsquo;m slightly ancient), javascript was pretty clunky and css was still in its infancy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While, I&amp;rsquo;ve gone on to learn bits of Oz, Lisp, Ruby, Python, R, Julia, I&amp;rsquo;ve never gone back to picking up
web-based technologies. Hence, creating websites is a dark art for me. Thankfully, the advent of static website generators
has come to my rescue, and my site is now more than just one big page like some really old professors&amp;rsquo; sites! (Fancy css + javascript based one-page sites are staging a come-back, though)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This avatar of my site is powered by &lt;a href=&#34;https://gohugo.io/&#34;&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt; with the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/chipsenkbeil/grid-side&#34;&gt;Grid-Side&lt;/a&gt; theme.
Many thanks to the creators of these tools!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Publications</title>
      <link>http://viveknallur.github.io/research/publications/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://viveknallur.github.io/research/publications/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;We are all measured by a number these days. So, here&amp;rsquo;s the mandatory Google Scholar link that leads to the citation count, for me:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;google-scholar-link-https-scholar-google-com-citations-user-teqjsjcaaaa:480c4de99851329b51acecc000e2e84f&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=TeqJsjcAAAA&#34;&gt;Google Scholar Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;the-list-in-reverse-chronological-order:480c4de99851329b51acecc000e2e84f&#34;&gt;The List (in reverse chronological order)&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Clonal Plasticity: A Mechanism For Decentralized Adaptation in Multi-Agent
Systems&lt;/em&gt; [&lt;a href=&#34;http://viveknallur.github.io/pubs/ClonalPlasticity.pdf&#34;&gt;Author preprint&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2897067&#34;&gt;11th International Symposium on Software Engineering for Adaptive and
Self-Managing Systems&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Algorithm Diversity - A Mechanism for Distributive Justice in a Socio-Technical MAS&lt;/em&gt; [&lt;a href=&#34;http://viveknallur.github.io/pubs/aamas2016.pdf&#34;&gt;Author preprint&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2936986&#34;&gt;AAMAS&amp;rsquo;2016 - International Conference on Autonomous Agents and Multiagent Systems&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Enabling Participatory Routing Using a Smart-City Platform&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
1^st IEEE Smart Cities Conference, Guadalajara, October 2015&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Increasing Information in a Socio-Technical MAS Considered Contentious&lt;/em&gt;  [&lt;a href=&#34;http://viveknallur.github.io/pubs/sasow-15.pdf&#34;&gt;Author preprint&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2866787&#34;&gt;Ninth IEEE Self-Adaptive and Self-Organizing Workshops (SASOW), September 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;On Architectural Diversity of Dynamic Adaptive Systems&lt;/em&gt;  [&lt;a href=&#34;http://viveknallur.github.io/pubs/icse-nier-2015.pdf&#34;&gt;Author
preprint&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2819112&#34;&gt;37^th International Conference on Software Engineering - New Ideas and Emerging Results, May 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Smart Route Planning Using Open Data and Participatory Sensing&lt;/em&gt;  [&lt;a href=&#34;http://viveknallur.github.io/pubs/SmartRoutePlanning.pdf&#34;&gt;Author preprint&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;br /&gt;
11^th Conference on Open Source Systems: Adoption and Impact&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Towards Decentralized Detection of Emergence in Complex Adaptive Systems&lt;/em&gt;
[&lt;a href=&#34;http://viveknallur.github.io/pubs/Saso-Emergence.pdf&#34;&gt;Author preprint&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2763125&#34;&gt;Eighth IEEE Conference on Self-Adaptive and Self-Organizing Systems, September 2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s good to be different: Diversity, Heterogeneity and Dynamics in Collective
Systems&lt;/em&gt;  [&lt;a href=&#34;http://viveknallur.github.io/pubs/sasow-14.pdf&#34;&gt;Author preprint&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2763072&#34;&gt;Eighth IEEE Self-Adaptive and Self-Organizing Workshops (SASOW), September 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A Decentralized Self-Adaptation Mechanism for Service-Based Applications in the
Cloud&lt;/em&gt;  [&lt;a href=&#34;http://viveknallur.github.io/pubs/TSE-2013.pdf&#34;&gt;Author preprint&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2498775&#34;&gt;IEEE Transactions on Software Engineering, Vol 39:5, Pages 591&amp;ndash;612, 2013&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Self-Adapting Applications Based on QA Requirements in the Cloud Using Market-Based Heuristics&lt;/em&gt;  [&lt;a href=&#34;http://viveknallur.github.io/pubs/servicewave-2010.pdf&#34;&gt;Author preprint&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;br /&gt;
Towards a Service-Based Internet, SERVICEWAVE, 2010&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Design of a Market-Based Mechanism for Quality Attribute Tradeoff of Services
in the Cloud&lt;/em&gt; [&lt;a href=&#34;http://viveknallur.github.io/pubs/SAC-preprint.pdf&#34;&gt;Author preprint&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=1774168&amp;amp;CFID=797660203&#34;&gt;25^th ACM Symposium on Applied Computing, 2010&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Self-optimizing architecture for ensuring Quality Attributes in the Cloud&lt;/em&gt;  [&lt;a href=&#34;http://viveknallur.github.io/pubs/wicsa-ecsa-2009.pdf&#34;&gt;Author preprint&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;br /&gt;
Joint Working IEEE/IFIP Conference on Software Architecture - WICSA/ECSA, 2009&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Algorithmic Diversity</title>
      <link>http://viveknallur.github.io/research/algorithmic-diversity/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://viveknallur.github.io/research/algorithmic-diversity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Algorithmic diversity aims to quantify the amount of natural diversity available in a pool of algorithms, and their effect on system properties.  In many domains,
there are multiple algorithms available that can perform the same / similar tasks. For example, there are a plethora of algorithms available for sorting, load-balancing,
compression, etc. Almost every computer science student studies multiple sorting algorithms, and their respective complexity (big-O). Apart from complexity, there are
many aspects in which algorithms differ, data structures, strategies, etc. These aspects have an impact on the real-world performance of software systems. In most
cases, the developer or system administrator tries to foresee the operating environment of the software system, its input characteristics and chose the best / optimal
algorithm, that they could possibly implement. However, in the real world, operating environments rarely stay stagnant and the desired quality attributes of the system
do not stay at the same level, as when deployed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are investigating whether using a pool of algorithms, instead of a single optimal pre-chosen algorithm, could impact the software system&amp;rsquo;s quality attributes
in a positive way, and if so, how do we quantify it? And herein lies the challenge. A little reflection would lead us to the conclusion that, in an uncertain
operating environment, using a pool of algorithms would definitely affect the system&amp;rsquo;s robustness, but by how much? And can we pre-determine the
amount of diversity in this pool? These are some of the questions that we aim to answer, with our experiments in algorithmic diversity.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>