<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Research on Vivek Nallur</title>
    <link>http://viveknallur.github.io/tags/research/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Research on Vivek Nallur</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright &amp;#169; by Vivek Nallur</copyright>
    <atom:link href="http://viveknallur.github.io/tags/research/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>The Smoothest Streets in Dublin</title>
      <link>http://viveknallur.github.io/smarthopper/least_bumpy_ride/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://viveknallur.github.io/smarthopper/least_bumpy_ride/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;least-bumpy-routing&#34;&gt;Least Bumpy Routing&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://viveknallur.github.io/smarthopper/introduction&#34;&gt;SmartHopper&lt;/a&gt; extended to use road smoothness data provided by cyclists.&lt;br /&gt;

One of the aims of SmartHopper is to be able to accept any spatial sensor data provided by citizens, and turn it into
useful information. One of our Masters&amp;rsquo; students is an avid cyclist, and he wrote an app that collected smoothness data
from sensors attached to bikes. He then asked his friends to attach sensors and simply use it during their daily rides
through the city. We were able to turn this road-by-road smoothness data into a heatmap and routing information with
minimal effort (took us about 2-3 person days).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take a look at the routing that&amp;rsquo;s now made possible, with SmartHopper
&lt;img src=&#34;http://viveknallur.github.io/images/smarthopper/Least_Bumpy_800x600.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Smoothest Cycling Route Through Dublin&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice, that in the visualization, the user can opt to see different layers of road smoothness. And also, SmartHopper simply took
this information, and used it for providing the smoothest (or rather, &amp;ldquo;least bumpy&amp;rdquo;) route.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What else can you imagine SmartHopper being extended for?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SEAMS&#39;16 Paper Accepted</title>
      <link>http://viveknallur.github.io/posts/seams-acceptance/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://viveknallur.github.io/posts/seams-acceptance/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Our paper entitled &lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;Clonal Plasticity: A Method for Decentralized Adaptation
in Multi-Agent Systems&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt; accepted at &lt;a href=&#34;http://seams2016.jgreen.de/&#34;&gt;SEAMS&amp;rsquo;2016&lt;/a&gt;
Yaay!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll put up a pre-print copy of the paper in the &lt;em&gt;research&lt;/em&gt; section of the site. In the meantime, if you just can&amp;rsquo;t wait, send me an email.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>AAMAS&#39;16 Paper Accepted</title>
      <link>http://viveknallur.github.io/posts/aamas-acceptance/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://viveknallur.github.io/posts/aamas-acceptance/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Our paper entitled &lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;Algorithm-Diversity: A Mechanism for Distributive Justice in a Socio-Technical MAS&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt; accepted at &lt;a href=&#34;http://sis.smu.edu.sg/aamas2016&#34;&gt;AAMAS&amp;rsquo;2016&lt;/a&gt;
Yaay!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll put up a pre-print copy of the paper in the &lt;em&gt;research&lt;/em&gt; section of the site. In the meantime, if you just can&amp;rsquo;t wait, send me an email.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Successful Thesis Defense!</title>
      <link>http://viveknallur.github.io/posts/eamonn-passes/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://viveknallur.github.io/posts/eamonn-passes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h5 id=&#34;eamonn-o-toole-passes-his-viva-on-decentralized-emergence-detection-with-flying-colours-hugomore42&#34;&gt;Eamonn O&amp;rsquo;Toole passes his viva on decentralized emergence detection with flying colours! &lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eamonn successfully defended his thesis (entitled &amp;ldquo;Decentralized Detection of Emergence in Complex Adaptive Systems&amp;rdquo;) on 15-Jan-2016. Way to go, soon-to-be Dr. Eamonn! Very well done!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>FutureCities on YouTube!</title>
      <link>http://viveknallur.github.io/posts/futurecities-youtube/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://viveknallur.github.io/posts/futurecities-youtube/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;FutureCities now has a Youtube! channel &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The FutureCities centre now has a Youtube! channel, so it&amp;rsquo;s easier to find all
of our work (when you&amp;rsquo;re not looking up our papers ;))&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC9odOg7SQMug4mQGzdJJehg&#34;&gt;FutureCities Youtube Channel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thesis Submission!</title>
      <link>http://viveknallur.github.io/posts/eamonn-submits/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://viveknallur.github.io/posts/eamonn-submits/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h5 id=&#34;eamonn-o-toole-submits-his-thesis-on-decentralized-emergence-detection-hugomore42&#34;&gt;Eamonn O&amp;rsquo;Toole submits his thesis on decentralized emergence detection! &lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eamonn has just submitted his thesis entitled &amp;ldquo;Decentralized Detection of Emergence in Complex Adaptive Systems&amp;rdquo;. Way to go, Eamonn! Very well done! Of course, it&amp;rsquo;s really special to me since he&amp;rsquo;s my first PhD student mentee. It&amp;rsquo;s been a pleasure discussing philosophies, ideas, problems and solution concepts with you, mate. Hope you go far!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thesis looks at the problem of detecting emergence in a large-scale complex adaptive systems, where each part could potentially be adapting independently. Given the large-scale and decentralized nature of such systems, the big questions are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Is it possible to detect emergence in a decentralized fashion?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;How do you know which variables are interesting, given that the environment
and the components themselves, change dynamically?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For answers to these questions (and more), read his thesis! (We&amp;rsquo;ve also submitted a paper to TAAS. Fingers crossed!).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Future Cities</title>
      <link>http://viveknallur.github.io/smartcities/futurecities/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://viveknallur.github.io/smartcities/futurecities/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tcd.ie/futurecities/&#34;&gt;Future cities research centre&lt;/a&gt; is a multi-disciplinary centre at Trinity College Dublin. Its mission is to
conduct holistic research into all aspects of a smart and sustainable city, and not just view a city as a agglomeration of sensors and people.  It connects
researchers across Trinity, and brings to bear multiple perspectives on the pressing problems of urban living. Typical smart city projects tend to concentrate
on leveraging sensors and the much-vaunted &lt;em&gt;Internet of Things&lt;/em&gt;, to create technical solutions to human problems. We believe that while technology can and should
play an important enabling role in a sustainable future, ultimately the citizens must take responsibility for their city. We investigate projects that can bring
to bear legal policy, urban planning, economic incentives, and educational awareness to nudge citizens towards a healthier and sustainable future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;active-areas-of-research&#34;&gt;Active Areas of Research&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We work on areas such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tcd.ie/futurecities/research/mobility/&#34;&gt;Smart Mobility&lt;/a&gt;: Future Cities&amp;rsquo; Mobility research strand focuses on addressing the effects of increasing road usage including delay, unpredictable journey times, exessive pollution, and driver frustration as well as to improve road safety.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tcd.ie/futurecities/research/energy/&#34;&gt;Energy Management&lt;/a&gt;: The Future Cities’ Energy research strand focuses on technology development of platforms that enable services for urban energy management. The approaches investigated include forecasting energy demand, improving energy efficiency within the built environment and integrating renewable energy sources into the electrical grid.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tcd.ie/futurecities/research/pollution/&#34;&gt;Pollution&lt;/a&gt;: The Future Cities’ Pollution research strand looks at improving methodologies for monitoring levels of urban pollution.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tcd.ie/futurecities/research/citizen-engagement/&#34;&gt;Citizen Engagement&lt;/a&gt;: This research strands addresses how citizens can be integrated early in the research pipeline, to ensure that practical considerations are taken into account, highlighting potential negative impact on society (e.g., through weakened privacy and security) and effectively to co-design potential futures.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tcd.ie/futurecities/research/urban-scale-data/&#34;&gt;Urban-Scale Data&lt;/a&gt;: This research strand addresses middleware and communications architectures to allow high volumes of data from public, business-owned and user-contributed sensors to be gathered and exploited by smart cities. This area merges wireless sensor networks, vehicular sensor networks, and participatory sensing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;interested&#34;&gt;Interested?&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tcd.ie/futurecities/contact/&#34;&gt;Talk to us&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reproducible Results in Software Engineering</title>
      <link>http://viveknallur.github.io/research/reproducible_research/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://viveknallur.github.io/research/reproducible_research/</guid>
      <description>&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the central problem we face in all of computer science is how we are
to get to the situation where we build on top of the work of others rather
than redoing so much of it in a trivially different way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ndash; Richard Hamming (From Turing Award lecture(1968))
&lt;em&gt;Journal of the ACM (Jan 1969), 16, No. 1, 10.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;reproducing-and-sharing-results-of-experiments-in-software-engineering&#34;&gt;Reproducing and Sharing Results of Experiments in Software Engineering&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Richard Hamming&amp;rsquo;s statement has perhaps never been as true, as it is true today. There are literally hundreds of conferences, with tens of thousands of papers published every year. Surely, going by the volume of output, we should be in a much better position with regard to the big problems, than we are at the moment. Of course, there are some problems that are genuinely hard, but even so, a whole lot of effort is expended in trying to do something trivially better or trivially different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of the problem is that, at least in computer science, there&amp;rsquo;s no value accorded to repeating and verifying experiments. Due to the proliferation of platforms, libraries, languages, the amount of effort involved in reproducing someone else&amp;rsquo;s experiment is so huge that the average researcher doesn&amp;rsquo;t attempt it. If one is unable to reproduce a result, so what? It must be because the environment wasn&amp;rsquo;t just right, or the data-structure wasn&amp;rsquo;t the same as the one in the paper. Or reproducer&amp;rsquo;s code is wrong (even more insidiously, &amp;ldquo;has a bug&amp;rdquo;). The net result is that not many results are reproduced, which of course, then leads to a situation, where published papers have non-reproduceable results! This state of affairs would be unacceptable in any other science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Software Engineering has yet to figure out how to document and preserve forever and ever, the ideas/decisions/assumptions behind a big piece of code, we have reached a point where it is possible to checkpoint a piece of working code and make it available economically to anyone who wants it. Virtual Machines, while cool and dandy, are terribly big and difficult to share. Docker containers, though, in  my opinion, hit a sweet spot where, for certain kinds of code and libraries, the exact configuration and environment can be captured and shared with the world. Thanks to the Docker hub, we can also be reasonably sure that it (the code) won&amp;rsquo;t go away, as soon as researcher moves institutions (To my great mortification and embarrassment, all of my code and data vanished from my PhD student website, soon after I graduated. Which meant that reproducing (and building upon) my TSE paper results was next to impossible).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;docker-hub-address&#34;&gt;Docker Hub Address&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having learnt my lesson, I&amp;rsquo;m going to put up all of  my paper submissions&amp;rsquo; code
up on Docker Hub in a docker container. So, at the very least, folks can reproduce my results, if not build on it. I&amp;rsquo;m also trying to convince my colleagues to do the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://hub.docker.com/r/viveknallur/&#34;&gt;Vivek Nallur&amp;rsquo;s Docker Hub Repo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Algorithmic Diversity</title>
      <link>http://viveknallur.github.io/research/algorithmic-diversity/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://viveknallur.github.io/research/algorithmic-diversity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Algorithmic diversity aims to quantify the amount of natural diversity available in a pool of algorithms, and their effect on system properties.  In many domains,
there are multiple algorithms available that can perform the same / similar tasks. For example, there are a plethora of algorithms available for sorting, load-balancing,
compression, etc. Almost every computer science student studies multiple sorting algorithms, and their respective complexity (big-O). Apart from complexity, there are
many aspects in which algorithms differ, data structures, strategies, etc. These aspects have an impact on the real-world performance of software systems. In most
cases, the developer or system administrator tries to foresee the operating environment of the software system, its input characteristics and chose the best / optimal
algorithm, that they could possibly implement. However, in the real world, operating environments rarely stay stagnant and the desired quality attributes of the system
do not stay at the same level, as when deployed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are investigating whether using a pool of algorithms, instead of a single optimal pre-chosen algorithm, could impact the software system&amp;rsquo;s quality attributes
in a positive way, and if so, how do we quantify it? And herein lies the challenge. A little reflection would lead us to the conclusion that, in an uncertain
operating environment, using a pool of algorithms would definitely affect the system&amp;rsquo;s robustness, but by how much? And can we pre-determine the
amount of diversity in this pool? These are some of the questions that we aim to answer, with our experiments in algorithmic diversity.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Publications</title>
      <link>http://viveknallur.github.io/research/publications/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://viveknallur.github.io/research/publications/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We are all measured by a number these days. So, here&amp;rsquo;s the mandatory Google Scholar link that leads to the citation count, for me:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;google-scholar-link-https-scholar-google-com-citations-user-teqjsjcaaaa&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=TeqJsjcAAAA&#34;&gt;Google Scholar Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;the-list-in-reverse-chronological-order&#34;&gt;The List (in reverse chronological order)&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Decentralised Detection of Emergence in Complex Adaptive Systems&lt;/em&gt; [&lt;a href=&#34;http://viveknallur.github.io/pubs/DetectInCas.pdf&#34;&gt;Author preprint&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;br /&gt;
Accepted for publication in ACM Transactions on Autonomous and Adaptive Systems (TAAS) in November, 2016&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Clonal Plasticity: A Mechanism For Decentralized Adaptation in Multi-Agent
Systems&lt;/em&gt; [&lt;a href=&#34;http://viveknallur.github.io/pubs/ClonalPlasticity.pdf&#34;&gt;Author preprint&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2897067&#34;&gt;11th International Symposium on Software Engineering for Adaptive and
Self-Managing Systems&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Algorithm Diversity - A Mechanism for Distributive Justice in a Socio-Technical MAS&lt;/em&gt; [&lt;a href=&#34;http://viveknallur.github.io/pubs/aamas2016.pdf&#34;&gt;Author preprint&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2936986&#34;&gt;AAMAS&amp;rsquo;2016 - International Conference on Autonomous Agents and Multiagent Systems&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Enabling Participatory Routing Using a Smart-City Platform&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
1^st IEEE Smart Cities Conference, Guadalajara, October 2015&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Increasing Information in a Socio-Technical MAS Considered Contentious&lt;/em&gt;  [&lt;a href=&#34;http://viveknallur.github.io/pubs/sasow-15.pdf&#34;&gt;Author preprint&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2866787&#34;&gt;Ninth IEEE Self-Adaptive and Self-Organizing Workshops (SASOW), September 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;On Architectural Diversity of Dynamic Adaptive Systems&lt;/em&gt;  [&lt;a href=&#34;http://viveknallur.github.io/pubs/icse-nier-2015.pdf&#34;&gt;Author
preprint&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2819112&#34;&gt;37^th International Conference on Software Engineering - New Ideas and Emerging Results, May 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Smart Route Planning Using Open Data and Participatory Sensing&lt;/em&gt;  [&lt;a href=&#34;http://viveknallur.github.io/pubs/SmartRoutePlanning.pdf&#34;&gt;Author preprint&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;br /&gt;
11^th Conference on Open Source Systems: Adoption and Impact&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Towards Decentralized Detection of Emergence in Complex Adaptive Systems&lt;/em&gt;
[&lt;a href=&#34;http://viveknallur.github.io/pubs/Saso-Emergence.pdf&#34;&gt;Author preprint&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2763125&#34;&gt;Eighth IEEE Conference on Self-Adaptive and Self-Organizing Systems, September 2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s good to be different: Diversity, Heterogeneity and Dynamics in Collective
Systems&lt;/em&gt;  [&lt;a href=&#34;http://viveknallur.github.io/pubs/sasow-14.pdf&#34;&gt;Author preprint&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2763072&#34;&gt;Eighth IEEE Self-Adaptive and Self-Organizing Workshops (SASOW), September 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A Decentralized Self-Adaptation Mechanism for Service-Based Applications in the
Cloud&lt;/em&gt;  [&lt;a href=&#34;http://viveknallur.github.io/pubs/TSE-2013.pdf&#34;&gt;Author preprint&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2498775&#34;&gt;IEEE Transactions on Software Engineering, Vol 39:5, Pages 591&amp;ndash;612, 2013&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Self-Adapting Applications Based on QA Requirements in the Cloud Using Market-Based Heuristics&lt;/em&gt;  [&lt;a href=&#34;http://viveknallur.github.io/pubs/servicewave-2010.pdf&#34;&gt;Author preprint&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;br /&gt;
Towards a Service-Based Internet, SERVICEWAVE, 2010&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Design of a Market-Based Mechanism for Quality Attribute Tradeoff of Services
in the Cloud&lt;/em&gt; [&lt;a href=&#34;http://viveknallur.github.io/pubs/SAC-preprint.pdf&#34;&gt;Author preprint&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=1774168&amp;amp;CFID=797660203&#34;&gt;25^th ACM Symposium on Applied Computing, 2010&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Self-optimizing architecture for ensuring Quality Attributes in the Cloud&lt;/em&gt;  [&lt;a href=&#34;http://viveknallur.github.io/pubs/wicsa-ecsa-2009.pdf&#34;&gt;Author preprint&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;br /&gt;
Joint Working IEEE/IFIP Conference on Software Architecture - WICSA/ECSA, 2009&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research Interests</title>
      <link>http://viveknallur.github.io/research/interests/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://viveknallur.github.io/research/interests/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m very interested in complex self-adaptive systems, engineering emergent
feedback loops, predicting and controlling emergence in humano-tech systems
(where technical systems interact heavily with human desires/abilities),
engineering robust systems from non-robust parts.  If you&amp;rsquo;re interested in
collaborating, or just want to chat about a specific topic, &lt;a href=&#34;http://viveknallur.github.io/contact/&#34;&gt;get in
touch&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;multi-agent-systems&#34;&gt;Multi-Agent Systems&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Multi-Agent Systems (MAS) are my preferred tool for approaching problems in self-adaptation, complexity, emergence, etc. They lend themselves to extensive
forms of experimentation: having all agents follow simple rules, implementing complex machine-learning algorithms, investigating the interplay of different algorithms
being used at the same time, are all possible with relatively simple conceptual structures. Decoding the end result and teasing out the real factor(s) responsible
for a particular behaviour is considerably more difficult :-). But, that&amp;rsquo;s a part of the fun!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;decentralized-self-adaptation&#34;&gt;Decentralized Self-Adaptation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Self-Adaptation as a concept, has been recognized for a long time, from
biological systems to human affairs. Most natural systems exhibit this
phenomena, viz, the effecting of change by a system to ensure that it continues
to achieve the utility that it previously did. Different self-adaptive systems
exhibit adaptivity in different ways. In human-designed systems, the first
systematic efforts to create a self-adaptive system have been in the domain of
control loop design. Regardless of the type, most systems can be differentiated on the basis on
where the locus of control for self-adaptation lies:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Centralized&lt;/strong&gt;: In these type of systems, there is usually a hierarchy of
components.
Components at higher levels are responsible for goal management and planning for
change while those at lower levels are responsible for immediate action
and feedback. Decision-making is concentrated in one or a closely related set of
components. Centralized self-adaptive systems exhibit a communication pattern
that is
characterized by sensory information (data) flowing from dumb components to the
central decision maker, and instructions (commands) flowing from the decision
maker
to the dumb components. ‘Dumb’is used here, in the sense of a component having
no awareness of itself and its effects on the environment. Predictable and
cohesive
response to change are advantages of this type of system. However, reaction
times get
slower and slower as the size of the system increases.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Decentralized&lt;/strong&gt;: On the other hand, decentralized systems do not have a
hierarchy of
components. Each component acts as an individual agent with its own goals, and its
own perception of the environment. This has the advantage of quick reaction to change.
But it also has the disadvantage of being fragmented. That is, different components
may react differently to the same change stimulus. This could make the self-adaptation
inefficient or even deleterious. The challenge in building a decentralized
system is to ensure that all the agents collectively move the system towards a common goal. This
is usually accomplished by agents communicating amongst themselves. However, the
lack of a centralized communication pattern means that the communication protocol
must be decentralized and environment-based&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;coin-coordination-organization-institutions-norms&#34;&gt;COIN: Coordination, Organization, Institutions, Norms&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the particular problems using Multi-Agent Systems, that I&amp;rsquo;m interested in solving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&#34;coordination&#34;&gt;Coordination&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do we create coordination mechanisms for (really) large open distributed systems, which have autonomous components?

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Guarantee deadlock-freeness, for example&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&#34;organization&#34;&gt;Organization&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How can we depend on self-organization to meet system goals?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&#34;institutions&#34;&gt;Institutions&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What structural patterns are most conducive to emergent institutions?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&#34;norms&#34;&gt;Norms&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do we engineer an intelligent socio-technical system such that a self-sustaining/enduring MAS is an emergent property?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can we ensure some form of computational social justice amongst autonomous agents?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;** How do we design an intelligent socio-technical system?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Diversify Project</title>
      <link>http://viveknallur.github.io/smartcities/diversify/introduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Apr 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://viveknallur.github.io/smartcities/diversify/introduction/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://diversify-project.eu/&#34;&gt;Diversify&lt;/a&gt; is an EU FP7 project, that aims at
leveraging diversity, to improve software systems.  An inter-disciplinary
effort, one of our partners is the ECOBIO&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; group
 from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.univ-rennes1.fr/english/&#34;&gt;Université de Rennes 1&lt;/a&gt;. The
intent is that knowledge, concepts, and techniques flow in a two-way stream,
between ecology and computer science. The full list of partners is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.inria.fr/en/centre/rennes&#34;&gt;INRIA&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sintef.no/home/&#34;&gt;SINTEF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tcd.ie/&#34;&gt;TCD&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.univ-rennes1.fr/english/&#34;&gt;Université de Rennes 1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TCD works, along with INRIA and SINTEF, to automatically insert diversity into software. There are several levels at which a software system can be characterized:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://people.rennes.inria.fr/Benoit.Baudry/data/&#34;&gt;Source code level&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://viveknallur.github.io/diversify/algorithmic-diversity&#34;&gt;Algorithmic level&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sintef.no/en/publication/?pubid=CRIStin+1280693&#34;&gt;Architectural level&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ecosystem level (one piece of software in relation to others)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At each of these levels, our perspectives and concerns are different, and so are
the basic units that can be manipulated. At TCD, we are focussed on the change
in system, induced due to &lt;a href=&#34;http://viveknallur.github.io/diversify/algorithmic-diversity&#34;&gt;algorithmic
diversity&lt;/a&gt;.  That is, can we predict the
effect on a system, produced &lt;em&gt;solely&lt;/em&gt; due to the presence of a diversity of
algorithms?  What does it mean to have a &amp;ldquo;diversity of algorithms&amp;rdquo; anyway? If
diversity is better (or worse), can we increase (or decrease) this diversity, in
an automated manner? These are the questions that we seek to answer, in this
project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;smarthopper&#34;&gt;SmartHopper&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Diversify project also uses a smart-mobility test-bed to experiment with,
for all of the diversification techniques mentioned above, &lt;em&gt;i.e.&lt;/em&gt;,
&lt;a href=&#34;http://viveknallur.github.io/smarthopper/&#34;&gt;SmartHopper&lt;/a&gt;. SmartHopper is derived from the open-source
routing project, &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/graphhopper/graphhopper/&#34;&gt;GraphHopper Library&lt;/a&gt;, by the lovely folk at &lt;a href=&#34;https://graphhopper.com/&#34;&gt;GraphHopper&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ve made a fair few modifications to it, to enable both, experimentation with
diversification techniques, as well as allow sensor information to be utilized
on top of OpenStreetMaps plus routing. For more details, look at the
&lt;a href=&#34;http://viveknallur.github.io/smarthopper/&#34;&gt;SmartHopper page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://ecobio.univ-rennes1.fr/dernieres_publications.php&#34;&gt;http://ecobio.univ-rennes1.fr/dernieres_publications.php&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Least Noise Routing!</title>
      <link>http://viveknallur.github.io/smarthopper/least_noise_routing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://viveknallur.github.io/smarthopper/least_noise_routing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;screenshots-of-the-smarthopper-in-action&#34;&gt;Screenshots of the SmartHopper in Action&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://viveknallur.github.io/smarthopper/introduction&#34;&gt;SmartHopper&lt;/a&gt; fuses the routing engine, provided by the GraphHopper folks, with the participatory noise data collected by citizens.&lt;br /&gt;

Here&amp;rsquo;s what it looks like without the noise data being used:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://viveknallur.github.io/images/smarthopper/Normal-Routing-Without-Noise-800x600.png&#34; alt=&#34;Normal Usage&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, add the noise overlay created from the data uploaded from the smartphones of participating citizens&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://viveknallur.github.io/images/smarthopper/Routing-with-Noise-Overlay-800x600.png&#34; alt=&#34;Noise Overlay&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the menu on the left hand side, change the &lt;em&gt;weighting&lt;/em&gt; to &lt;strong&gt;Least Noisy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://viveknallur.github.io/images/smarthopper/Least-Noise-Routing-800x600.png&#34; alt=&#34;Least Noisy Route&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SmartHopper</title>
      <link>http://viveknallur.github.io/smarthopper/introduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://viveknallur.github.io/smarthopper/introduction/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ever since the SETI@Home project took off, the idea of using `crowd power&amp;rsquo; to help out with computing needs has been explored by many projects. The explosion of
the smartphone market opened up a niche in this voluntary computing world. Suddenly, participatory sensing became a means to harness the power of the crowd
in an almost-literal sense.  Given enough enthusiastic participants, researchers could potentially get access to sensor measurements that could be statistically
massaged to get a treasure-trove of GPS-tagged data. However, the excitement of such potential quickly waned as the number of enthusiastic participants dropped with
each additional participatory sensing app, that arrived on the app-market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We believe that more people can be motivated to contribute data to research, if this contribution can be linked to a tangible benefit that citizens can receive
in turn, for volunteering their time and data. &lt;em&gt;SmartHopper&lt;/em&gt; is a smart mobility platform, developed at TCD, that incorporates participatory sensing and combines
it with an open-source routing engine, to enable citizens to generate smarter routes for themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;basic-idea&#34;&gt;Basic Idea&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We collaborate with the good folks working on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.noisetube.net/&#34;&gt;NoiseTube Project&lt;/a&gt; at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.vub.ac.be/&#34;&gt;Vrije Universiteit Brussel&lt;/a&gt; and ask volunteers to walk around Dublin city, so that
we get noise measurements from different streets. Given enough walkers, we are able to generate a &lt;code&gt;Noise Map&lt;/code&gt; of Dublin on a street-by-street basis. Then we transform
this data, and insert it into a Redis store. We also forked the open-source &lt;a href=&#34;http://graphhopper.com/&#34;&gt;GraphHopper&lt;/a&gt; project, to allow it to be deployed and queried
using REST-based API. Now, when you query SmartHopper, it is able to combine a query for a route from (say) Trinity College to (say) Dundrum, with the noise information
gathered from the volunteers and generate the `least noisy&amp;rsquo; route between them. This can be useful for parents with infants, or elderly people wishing to take a walk,
as it enables them to choose a route, that is least affected by noise pollution. For more information about the architecture of the system, check out our &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tara.tcd.ie/handle/2262/73955?show=full&#34;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt;, published
at the Open Source Systems conference. Also, check out the SmartHopper UI page, where you can see screenshots of the system in action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;other-ideas&#34;&gt;Other Ideas&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Noise is merely an exemplar of what is possible, by combining sensor data with other software. Smarter routes can be enabled, limited only by the availability of data.
We are trying to get air pollution data of several kinds, which can be quite useful for sufferers of pollen allergies, asthma, etc. to generate routes that may
not necessarily be the fastest or the shortest, but are more to their liking. We&amp;rsquo;re looking into tapping into Open Data from any source that is able to generate
consistent and city-wide data, which can then be automatically turned into query-able routes! Smart Mobility is not merely about using technology to find
taxis or public transport, but also being able to query the state-of-the-city, in a personalized manner. If you want to talk to us about data that you have, or ideas
to increase the smartness of SmartHopper, get in &lt;a href=&#34;http://viveknallur.github.io/contact/&#34;&gt;touch&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SmartHopper Demo!</title>
      <link>http://viveknallur.github.io/smarthopper/on_youtube/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://viveknallur.github.io/smarthopper/on_youtube/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h5 id=&#34;smarthopper-is-now-on-youtube&#34;&gt;SmartHopper is now on Youtube!&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a picture is worth a thousand words, a video is worth, well, a book-chapter
at least. Here&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.scss.tcd.ie/~cardozon/&#34;&gt;Nicolas Cardozo&lt;/a&gt;, from our
group, demonstrating how to use SmartHopper for a whole variety of use-cases. If you don&amp;rsquo;t hear any audio, don&amp;rsquo;t fret. He&amp;rsquo;s the strong and silent type.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RWlJ4ibfuT0&#34; title=&#34;SmartHopper Demo&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://viveknallur.github.io/images/smarthopper/smarthopper-video-shot.png&#34; alt=&#34;SmartHopper Demonstration Video&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>