<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Software Engineering on Vivek Nallur</title>
    <link>http://viveknallur.github.io/tags/software-engineering/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Software Engineering on Vivek Nallur</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright &amp;#169; by Vivek Nallur</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 02 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://viveknallur.github.io/tags/software-engineering/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Slides for CS3012</title>
      <link>http://viveknallur.github.io/teaching/slides/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://viveknallur.github.io/teaching/slides/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Slides from the lectures for the CS 3012 course on Software Engineering can be
found here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;slides:90014a872bdadc29d38e0ddafb91b9e9&#34;&gt;Slides&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://viveknallur.github.io/slides/01-introduction.pdf&#34;&gt;Introduction to the Module&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CS3012 - Software Engineering</title>
      <link>http://viveknallur.github.io/teaching/cs3012/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://viveknallur.github.io/teaching/cs3012/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;This is the landing page for the CS 3012 course on Software Engineering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here you can find announcements regarding the course, and other miscellaneous
information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;announcements:e3569ea0094b2f25a013d21134dc31b1&#34;&gt;Announcements&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The module repository is now live and all students &lt;strong&gt;must&lt;/strong&gt; request access to
be able to submit assignments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Algorithmic Diversity</title>
      <link>http://viveknallur.github.io/research/algorithmic-diversity/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://viveknallur.github.io/research/algorithmic-diversity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Algorithmic diversity aims to quantify the amount of natural diversity available in a pool of algorithms, and their effect on system properties.  In many domains,
there are multiple algorithms available that can perform the same / similar tasks. For example, there are a plethora of algorithms available for sorting, load-balancing,
compression, etc. Almost every computer science student studies multiple sorting algorithms, and their respective complexity (big-O). Apart from complexity, there are
many aspects in which algorithms differ, data structures, strategies, etc. These aspects have an impact on the real-world performance of software systems. In most
cases, the developer or system administrator tries to foresee the operating environment of the software system, its input characteristics and chose the best / optimal
algorithm, that they could possibly implement. However, in the real world, operating environments rarely stay stagnant and the desired quality attributes of the system
do not stay at the same level, as when deployed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are investigating whether using a pool of algorithms, instead of a single optimal pre-chosen algorithm, could impact the software system&amp;rsquo;s quality attributes
in a positive way, and if so, how do we quantify it? And herein lies the challenge. A little reflection would lead us to the conclusion that, in an uncertain
operating environment, using a pool of algorithms would definitely affect the system&amp;rsquo;s robustness, but by how much? And can we pre-determine the
amount of diversity in this pool? These are some of the questions that we aim to answer, with our experiments in algorithmic diversity.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>