<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Smartcities on Vivek Nallur</title>
    <link>http://viveknallur.github.io/smartcities/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Smartcities on Vivek Nallur</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright &amp;#169; by Vivek Nallur</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 16 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://viveknallur.github.io/smartcities/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Urban Infrastructure and Democracy</title>
      <link>http://viveknallur.github.io/smartcities/city-systems-report/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://viveknallur.github.io/smartcities/city-systems-report/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The term &lt;em&gt;smart cities&lt;/em&gt; gets a lot of play in the tech press and there are many companies that present solutions in this space. But the root cause of the problem isn&amp;rsquo;t
the lack of technology. Rather, it is pressure of population and the scarcity of resources in urban agglomerations, in a future that seems almost as inevitable as climate change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given this dystopian near-future, sustainability is the most important aspect that a wannabe smart city should focus on. And sustainability requires active and enthusiastic
participation from citizens. Instead of focussing on how many objects in a city are &lt;em&gt;connected&lt;/em&gt;, the emphasis should be on disseminating information and knowledge (which is quite a different concept) to
citizens, so that they can participate fruitfully in how their city and life is governed. In my opinion, this is the smartest thing a smart-city could do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, the Indian government announced an &lt;a href=&#34;http://smartcities.gov.in/&#34;&gt;urban renewal and infrastructural development mission&lt;/a&gt; that envisages the creation of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.makeinindia.com/article/-/v/internet-of-things&#34;&gt;100 smart cities&lt;/a&gt;
as a part of a larger agenda of creating an industrial corridor between the existing mega-cities of Delhi, Mumbai, Chennai, and Kolkata. While the mission may be ambitious (and laudable)
in terms of providing access to world-class infrastructure, to a large proportion of the population, it would be foolish to expect growth to be smooth and sustainable without explicit
steps taken to ensure that this happens. Depending on city growth to somehow organically result in an increase in the quality of life is a recipe for disaster. Anyone who has
navigated Bangalore traffic knows that unless urban infrastructural problems (and solutions) are measured and scrutinized regularly in an objective manner, there is no hope
of improvement in city life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.janaagraha.org/about-us/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Janaagraha Centre for Citizenship and Democracy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; attempts to provide the first part of the jigsaw, in this regard.
Their &lt;a href=&#34;http://janaagraha.org/reports/ASICS-2015.pdf&#34;&gt;annual survey on city-systems&lt;/a&gt; is a data-rich report with problem evaluation and measurement. Anyone interested
in a bird&amp;rsquo;s eye view of problems, across 21 Indian cities  should take a look. London and New York are included as benchmarks.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Future Cities</title>
      <link>http://viveknallur.github.io/smartcities/futurecities/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://viveknallur.github.io/smartcities/futurecities/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tcd.ie/futurecities/&#34;&gt;Future cities research centre&lt;/a&gt; is a multi-disciplinary centre at Trinity College Dublin. Its mission is to
conduct holistic research into all aspects of a smart and sustainable city, and not just view a city as a agglomeration of sensors and people.  It connects
researchers across Trinity, and brings to bear multiple perspectives on the pressing problems of urban living. Typical smart city projects tend to concentrate
on leveraging sensors and the much-vaunted &lt;em&gt;Internet of Things&lt;/em&gt;, to create technical solutions to human problems. We believe that while technology can and should
play an important enabling role in a sustainable future, ultimately the citizens must take responsibility for their city. We investigate projects that can bring
to bear legal policy, urban planning, economic incentives, and educational awareness to nudge citizens towards a healthier and sustainable future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;active-areas-of-research:0902b81ceffb0826a9dc92843526137b&#34;&gt;Active Areas of Research&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We work on areas such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tcd.ie/futurecities/research/mobility/&#34;&gt;Smart Mobility&lt;/a&gt;: Future Cities&amp;rsquo; Mobility research strand focuses on addressing the effects of increasing road usage including delay, unpredictable journey times, exessive pollution, and driver frustration as well as to improve road safety.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tcd.ie/futurecities/research/energy/&#34;&gt;Energy Management&lt;/a&gt;: The Future Cities’ Energy research strand focuses on technology development of platforms that enable services for urban energy management. The approaches investigated include forecasting energy demand, improving energy efficiency within the built environment and integrating renewable energy sources into the electrical grid.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tcd.ie/futurecities/research/pollution/&#34;&gt;Pollution&lt;/a&gt;: The Future Cities’ Pollution research strand looks at improving methodologies for monitoring levels of urban pollution.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tcd.ie/futurecities/research/citizen-engagement/&#34;&gt;Citizen Engagement&lt;/a&gt;: This research strands addresses how citizens can be integrated early in the research pipeline, to ensure that practical considerations are taken into account, highlighting potential negative impact on society (e.g., through weakened privacy and security) and effectively to co-design potential futures.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tcd.ie/futurecities/research/urban-scale-data/&#34;&gt;Urban-Scale Data&lt;/a&gt;: This research strand addresses middleware and communications architectures to allow high volumes of data from public, business-owned and user-contributed sensors to be gathered and exploited by smart cities. This area merges wireless sensor networks, vehicular sensor networks, and participatory sensing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;interested:0902b81ceffb0826a9dc92843526137b&#34;&gt;Interested?&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tcd.ie/futurecities/contact/&#34;&gt;Talk to us&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Diversify Project</title>
      <link>http://viveknallur.github.io/smartcities/diversify/introduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Apr 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://viveknallur.github.io/smartcities/diversify/introduction/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://diversify-project.eu/&#34;&gt;Diversify&lt;/a&gt; is an EU FP7 project, that aims at
leveraging diversity, to improve software systems.  An inter-disciplinary
effort, one of our partners is the ECOBIO&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:2767292a573dc549b9b4297b701af3ab:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:2767292a573dc549b9b4297b701af3ab:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; group
 from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.univ-rennes1.fr/english/&#34;&gt;Université de Rennes 1&lt;/a&gt;. The
intent is that knowledge, concepts, and techniques flow in a two-way stream,
between ecology and computer science. The full list of partners is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.inria.fr/en/centre/rennes&#34;&gt;INRIA&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sintef.no/home/&#34;&gt;SINTEF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tcd.ie/&#34;&gt;TCD&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.univ-rennes1.fr/english/&#34;&gt;Université de Rennes 1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TCD works, along with INRIA and SINTEF, to automatically insert diversity into software. There are several levels at which a software system can be characterized:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://people.rennes.inria.fr/Benoit.Baudry/data/&#34;&gt;Source code level&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://viveknallur.github.io/diversify/algorithmic-diversity&#34;&gt;Algorithmic level&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sintef.no/en/publication/?pubid=CRIStin+1280693&#34;&gt;Architectural level&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ecosystem level (one piece of software in relation to others)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At each of these levels, our perspectives and concerns are different, and so are
the basic units that can be manipulated. At TCD, we are focussed on the change
in system, induced due to &lt;a href=&#34;http://viveknallur.github.io/diversify/algorithmic-diversity&#34;&gt;algorithmic
diversity&lt;/a&gt;.  That is, can we predict the
effect on a system, produced &lt;em&gt;solely&lt;/em&gt; due to the presence of a diversity of
algorithms?  What does it mean to have a &amp;ldquo;diversity of algorithms&amp;rdquo; anyway? If
diversity is better (or worse), can we increase (or decrease) this diversity, in
an automated manner? These are the questions that we seek to answer, in this
project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;smarthopper:2767292a573dc549b9b4297b701af3ab&#34;&gt;SmartHopper&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Diversify project also uses a smart-mobility test-bed to experiment with,
for all of the diversification techniques mentioned above, &lt;em&gt;i.e.&lt;/em&gt;,
&lt;a href=&#34;http://viveknallur.github.io/smarthopper/&#34;&gt;SmartHopper&lt;/a&gt;. SmartHopper is derived from the open-source
routing project, &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/graphhopper/graphhopper/&#34;&gt;GraphHopper Library&lt;/a&gt;, by the lovely folk at &lt;a href=&#34;https://graphhopper.com/&#34;&gt;GraphHopper&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ve made a fair few modifications to it, to enable both, experimentation with
diversification techniques, as well as allow sensor information to be utilized
on top of OpenStreetMaps plus routing. For more details, look at the
&lt;a href=&#34;http://viveknallur.github.io/smarthopper/&#34;&gt;SmartHopper page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2767292a573dc549b9b4297b701af3ab:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://ecobio.univ-rennes1.fr/dernieres_publications.php&#34;&gt;http://ecobio.univ-rennes1.fr/dernieres_publications.php&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:2767292a573dc549b9b4297b701af3ab:1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>