<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Emergence on Vivek Nallur</title>
    <link>http://viveknallur.github.io/tags/emergence/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Emergence on Vivek Nallur</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright &amp;#169; by Vivek Nallur</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 15 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://viveknallur.github.io/tags/emergence/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Successful Thesis Defense!</title>
      <link>http://viveknallur.github.io/posts/eamonn-passes/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://viveknallur.github.io/posts/eamonn-passes/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h5 id=&#34;eamonn-o-toole-passes-his-viva-on-decentralized-emergence-detection-with-flying-colours:d098cef219f9391405a424ae6f194f17&#34;&gt;Eamonn O&amp;rsquo;Toole passes his viva on decentralized emergence detection with flying colours!&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eamonn successfully defended his thesis (entitled &amp;ldquo;Decentralized Detection of Emergence in Complex Adaptive Systems&amp;rdquo;) on 15-Jan-2016. Way to go, soon-to-be Dr. Eamonn! Very well done!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thesis Submission!</title>
      <link>http://viveknallur.github.io/posts/eamonn-submits/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://viveknallur.github.io/posts/eamonn-submits/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h5 id=&#34;eamonn-o-toole-submits-his-thesis-on-decentralized-emergence-detection:dee999b9b5019ee00d8b9e52e357b2eb&#34;&gt;Eamonn O&amp;rsquo;Toole submits his thesis on decentralized emergence detection!&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eamonn has just submitted his thesis entitled &amp;ldquo;Decentralized Detection of Emergence in Complex Adaptive Systems&amp;rdquo;. Way to go, Eamonn! Very well done! Of course, it&amp;rsquo;s really special to me since he&amp;rsquo;s my first PhD student mentee. It&amp;rsquo;s been a pleasure discussing philosophies, ideas, problems and solution concepts with you, mate. Hope you go far!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thesis looks at the problem of detecting emergence in a large-scale complex adaptive systems, where each part could potentially be adapting independently. Given the large-scale and decentralized nature of such systems, the big questions are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Is it possible to detect emergence in a decentralized fashion?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;How do you know which variables are interesting, given that the environment
and the components themselves, change dynamically?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For answers to these questions (and more), read his thesis! (We&amp;rsquo;ve also submitted a paper to TAAS. Fingers crossed!).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reproducible Results in Software Engineering</title>
      <link>http://viveknallur.github.io/research/reproducible_research/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://viveknallur.github.io/research/reproducible_research/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the central problem we face in all of computer science is how we are
to get to the situation where we build on top of the work of others rather
than redoing so much of it in a trivially different way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ndash; Richard Hamming (From Turing Award lecture(1968))
&lt;em&gt;Journal of the ACM (Jan 1969), 16, No. 1, 10.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;reproducing-and-sharing-results-of-experiments-in-software-engineering:0a02261f8657866700056ef61d86ade2&#34;&gt;Reproducing and Sharing Results of Experiments in Software Engineering&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Richard Hamming&amp;rsquo;s statement has perhaps never been as true, as it is true today. There are literally hundreds of conferences, with tens of thousands of papers published every year. Surely, going by the volume of output, we should be in a much better position with regard to the big problems, than we are at the moment. Of course, there are some problems that are genuinely hard, but even so, a whole lot of effort is expended in trying to do something trivially better or trivially different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of the problem is that, at least in computer science, there&amp;rsquo;s no value accorded to repeating and verifying experiments. Due to the proliferation of platforms, libraries, languages, the amount of effort involved in reproducing someone else&amp;rsquo;s experiment is so huge that the average researcher doesn&amp;rsquo;t attempt it. If one is unable to reproduce a result, so what? It must be because the environment wasn&amp;rsquo;t just right, or the data-structure wasn&amp;rsquo;t the same as the one in the paper. Or reproducer&amp;rsquo;s code is wrong (even more insidiously, &amp;ldquo;has a bug&amp;rdquo;). The net result is that not many results are reproduced, which of course, then leads to a situation, where published papers have non-reproduceable results! This state of affairs would be unacceptable in any other science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Software Engineering has yet to figure out how to document and preserve forever and ever, the ideas/decisions/assumptions behind a big piece of code, we have reached a point where it is possible to checkpoint a piece of working code and make it available economically to anyone who wants it. Virtual Machines, while cool and dandy, are terribly big and difficult to share. Docker containers, though, in  my opinion, hit a sweet spot where, for certain kinds of code and libraries, the exact configuration and environment can be captured and shared with the world. Thanks to the Docker hub, we can also be reasonably sure that it (the code) won&amp;rsquo;t go away, as soon as researcher moves institutions (To my great mortification and embarrassment, all of my code and data vanished from my PhD student website, soon after I graduated. Which meant that reproducing (and building upon) my TSE paper results was next to impossible).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;docker-hub-address:0a02261f8657866700056ef61d86ade2&#34;&gt;Docker Hub Address&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having learnt my lesson, I&amp;rsquo;m going to put up all of  my paper submissions&amp;rsquo; code
up on Docker Hub in a docker container. So, at the very least, folks can reproduce my results, if not build on it. I&amp;rsquo;m also trying to convince my colleagues to do the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://hub.docker.com/r/viveknallur/&#34;&gt;Vivek Nallur&amp;rsquo;s Docker Hub Repo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Publications</title>
      <link>http://viveknallur.github.io/research/publications/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://viveknallur.github.io/research/publications/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;We are all measured by a number these days. So, here&amp;rsquo;s the mandatory Google Scholar link that leads to the citation count, for me:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;google-scholar-link-https-scholar-google-com-citations-user-teqjsjcaaaa:480c4de99851329b51acecc000e2e84f&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=TeqJsjcAAAA&#34;&gt;Google Scholar Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;the-list-in-reverse-chronological-order:480c4de99851329b51acecc000e2e84f&#34;&gt;The List (in reverse chronological order)&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Clonal Plasticity: A Mechanism For Decentralized Adaptation in Multi-Agent Systems&lt;/em&gt; [&lt;a href=&#34;http://viveknallur.github.io/pubs/ClonalPlasticity.pdf&#34;&gt;Author preprint&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;br /&gt;
Accepted for publication in &lt;a href=&#34;http://seams2016.jgreen.de/&#34;&gt;SEAMS&amp;rsquo;2016&lt;/a&gt;, co-located with &lt;a href=&#34;http://2016.icse.cs.txstate.edu/&#34;&gt;ICSE&amp;rsquo;2016&lt;/a&gt; - 11th International Symposium on Software Engineering for Adaptive and Self-Managing Systems&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Algorithm Diversity - A Mechanism for Distributive Justice in a Socio-Technical MAS&lt;/em&gt; [&lt;a href=&#34;http://viveknallur.github.io/pubs/aamas2016.pdf&#34;&gt;Author preprint&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;br /&gt;
Accepted for publication in &lt;a href=&#34;http://sis.smu.edu.sg/aamas2016&#34;&gt;AAMAS&amp;rsquo;2016&lt;/a&gt; - International Conference on Autonomous Agents and Multiagent Systems&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Enabling Participatory Routing Using a Smart-City Platform&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
1^st IEEE Smart Cities Conference, Guadalajara, October 2015&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Increasing Information in a Socio-Technical MAS Considered Contentious&lt;/em&gt;  [&lt;a href=&#34;http://viveknallur.github.io/pubs/sasow-15.pdf&#34;&gt;Author preprint&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;br /&gt;
Ninth IEEE Self-Adaptive and Self-Organizing Workshops (SASOW), September 2015&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;On Architectural Diversity of Dynamic Adaptive Systems&lt;/em&gt;  [&lt;a href=&#34;http://viveknallur.github.io/pubs/icse-nier-2015.pdf&#34;&gt;Author preprint&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;br /&gt;
37^th International Conference on Software Engineering - New Ideas and Emerging Results, May 2015&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Smart Route Planning Using Open Data and Participatory Sensing&lt;/em&gt;  [&lt;a href=&#34;http://viveknallur.github.io/pubs/SmartRoutePlanning.pdf&#34;&gt;Author preprint&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;br /&gt;
11^th Conference on Open Source Systems: Adoption and Impact&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Towards Decentralized Detection of Emergence in Complex Adaptive Systems&lt;/em&gt; [&lt;a href=&#34;http://viveknallur.github.io/pubs/Saso-Emergence.pdf&#34;&gt;Author preprint&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;br /&gt;
Eighth IEEE Conference on Self-Adaptive and Self-Organizing Systems, September 2014&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s good to be different: Diversity, Heterogeneity and Dynamics in Collective Systems&lt;/em&gt;  [&lt;a href=&#34;http://viveknallur.github.io/pubs/sasow-14.pdf&#34;&gt;Author preprint&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;br /&gt;
Eighth IEEE Self-Adaptive and Self-Organizing Workshops (SASOW), September 2015&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A Decentralized Self-Adaptation Mechanism for Service-Based Applications in the Cloud&lt;/em&gt;  [&lt;a href=&#34;http://viveknallur.github.io/pubs/TSE-2013.pdf&#34;&gt;Author preprint&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;br /&gt;
IEEE Transactions on Software Engineering, Vol 39:5, Pages 591&amp;ndash;612, 2013&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Self-Adapting Applications Based on QA Requirements in the Cloud Using Market-Based Heuristics&lt;/em&gt;  [&lt;a href=&#34;http://viveknallur.github.io/pubs/servicewave-2010.pdf&#34;&gt;Author preprint&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;br /&gt;
Towards a Service-Based Internet, SERVICEWAVE, 2010&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Design of a Market-Based Mechanism for Quality Attribute Tradeoff of Services in the Cloud&lt;/em&gt; [&lt;a href=&#34;http://viveknallur.github.io/pubs/SAC-preprint.pdf&#34;&gt;Author preprint&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;br /&gt;
25^th ACM Symposium on Applied Computing, 2010&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Self-optimizing architecture for ensuring Quality Attributes in the Cloud&lt;/em&gt;  [&lt;a href=&#34;http://viveknallur.github.io/pubs/wicsa-ecsa-2009.pdf&#34;&gt;Author preprint&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;br /&gt;
Joint Working IEEE/IFIP Conference on Software Architecture - WICSA/ECSA, 2009&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research Interests</title>
      <link>http://viveknallur.github.io/research/interests/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://viveknallur.github.io/research/interests/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m very interested in complex self-adaptive systems, engineering emergent
feedback loops, predicting and controlling emergence in humano-tech systems
(where technical systems interact heavily with human desires/abilities),
engineering robust systems from non-robust parts.  If you&amp;rsquo;re interested in
collaborating, or just want to chat about a specific topic, &lt;a href=&#34;http://viveknallur.github.io/contact/&#34;&gt;get in
touch&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;multi-agent-systems:9ff85ae240172bb97ce520c762b5dcae&#34;&gt;Multi-Agent Systems&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Multi-Agent Systems (MAS) are my preferred tool for approaching problems in self-adaptation, complexity, emergence, etc. They lend themselves to extensive
forms of experimentation: having all agents follow simple rules, implementing complex machine-learning algorithms, investigating the interplay of different algorithms
being used at the same time, are all possible with relatively simple conceptual structures. Decoding the end result and teasing out the real factor(s) responsible
for a particular behaviour is considerably more difficult :-). But, that&amp;rsquo;s a part of the fun!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;decentralized-self-adaptation:9ff85ae240172bb97ce520c762b5dcae&#34;&gt;Decentralized Self-Adaptation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Self-Adaptation as a concept, has been recognized for a long time, from
biological systems to human affairs. Most natural systems exhibit this
phenomena, viz, the effecting of change by a system to ensure that it continues
to achieve the utility that it previously did. Different self-adaptive systems
exhibit adaptivity in different ways. In human-designed systems, the first
systematic efforts to create a self-adaptive system have been in the domain of
control loop design. Regardless of the type, most systems can be differentiated on the basis on
where the locus of control for self-adaptation lies:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Centralized&lt;/strong&gt;: In these type of systems, there is usually a hierarchy of
components.
Components at higher levels are responsible for goal management and planning for
change while those at lower levels are responsible for immediate action
and feedback. Decision-making is concentrated in one or a closely related set of
components. Centralized self-adaptive systems exhibit a communication pattern
that is
characterized by sensory information (data) flowing from dumb components to the
central decision maker, and instructions (commands) flowing from the decision
maker
to the dumb components. ‘Dumb’is used here, in the sense of a component having
no awareness of itself and its effects on the environment. Predictable and
cohesive
response to change are advantages of this type of system. However, reaction
times get
slower and slower as the size of the system increases.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Decentralized&lt;/strong&gt;: On the other hand, decentralized systems do not have a
hierarchy of
components. Each component acts as an individual agent with its own goals, and its
own perception of the environment. This has the advantage of quick reaction to change.
But it also has the disadvantage of being fragmented. That is, different components
may react differently to the same change stimulus. This could make the self-adaptation
inefficient or even deleterious. The challenge in building a decentralized
system is to ensure that all the agents collectively move the system towards a common goal. This
is usually accomplished by agents communicating amongst themselves. However, the
lack of a centralized communication pattern means that the communication protocol
must be decentralized and environment-based&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;coin-coordination-organization-institutions-norms:9ff85ae240172bb97ce520c762b5dcae&#34;&gt;COIN: Coordination, Organization, Institutions, Norms&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the particular problems using Multi-Agent Systems, that I&amp;rsquo;m interested in solving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&#34;coordination:9ff85ae240172bb97ce520c762b5dcae&#34;&gt;Coordination&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do we create coordination mechanisms for (really) large open distributed systems, which have autonomous components?

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Guarantee deadlock-freeness, for example&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&#34;organization:9ff85ae240172bb97ce520c762b5dcae&#34;&gt;Organization&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How can we depend on self-organization to meet system goals?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&#34;institutions:9ff85ae240172bb97ce520c762b5dcae&#34;&gt;Institutions&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What structural patterns are most conducive to emergent institutions?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&#34;norms:9ff85ae240172bb97ce520c762b5dcae&#34;&gt;Norms&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do we engineer an intelligent socio-technical system such that a self-sustaining/enduring MAS is an emergent property?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can we ensure some form of computational social justice amongst autonomous agents?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;** How do we design an intelligent socio-technical system?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>