<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>About on Vivek Nallur</title>
    <link>http://viveknallur.github.io/tags/about/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in About on Vivek Nallur</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright &amp;#169; by Vivek Nallur</copyright>
    <atom:link href="http://viveknallur.github.io/tags/about/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>The Thinking Primate</title>
      <link>http://viveknallur.github.io/contact/thinking-ape/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://viveknallur.github.io/contact/thinking-ape/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Some folks have asked (maybe more have silently wondered) why the landing page features an ape. Especially since, as an academic, the general thrust
of a website is to promote a &amp;lsquo;respectable&amp;rsquo; image of the owner. I suppose, in some weird way, it&amp;rsquo;s a rebellion against the carefully manufactured  image that
most computer scientists / academics put out into the world (be it of a hacker, thinker, cool-dude, name-your-stereotype). Having an ape be the first impression leads to
a distortion of what people expect from an academic&amp;rsquo;s site. It lets visitors take me a little less seriously, and reminds me that everything is ephemeral (impressions, papers, philosophies).
It&amp;rsquo;s better to live life, than to think about living it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, in a way, it pays homage to my evolutionary grand-parents. It always pays to know your roots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides, my wife thinks the resemblance is quite striking :)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Site Design</title>
      <link>http://viveknallur.github.io/contact/site/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 May 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://viveknallur.github.io/contact/site/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, for some reason, during my academic and professional journey through computer science,
I&amp;rsquo;ve never picked up website design/technologies. While I was in school, HTML 3.x was still
the standard (yes, I&amp;rsquo;m slightly ancient), javascript was pretty clunky and css was still in its infancy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While, I&amp;rsquo;ve gone on to learn bits of Oz, Lisp, Ruby, Python, R, Julia, I&amp;rsquo;ve never gone back to picking up
web-based technologies. Hence, creating websites is a dark art for me. Thankfully, the advent of static website generators
has come to my rescue, and my site is now more than just one big page like some really old professors&amp;rsquo; sites! (Fancy css + javascript based one-page sites are staging a come-back, though)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This avatar of my site is powered by &lt;a href=&#34;https://gohugo.io/&#34;&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt; with the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/chipsenkbeil/grid-side&#34;&gt;Grid-Side&lt;/a&gt; theme.
Many thanks to the creators of these tools!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About Me</title>
      <link>http://viveknallur.github.io/contact/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://viveknallur.github.io/contact/about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m Vivek Nallur, itinerant academic, wannabe go-player and an enthusiastic
traveller.  I love asking questions, and then launching on a search for answers
to those questions. Hence, my career as a researcher came, more or less,
naturally to me. And I&amp;rsquo;ve already lied to you at least twice, in this
paragraph!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;research&#34;&gt;Research&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I work as a &lt;a href=&#34;{{ site.baseurl }}/research.html&#34;&gt;Research Fellow&lt;/a&gt; with the
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dsg.cs.tcd.ie&#34;&gt;Distributed Systems Group&lt;/a&gt; in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.scss.tcd.ie&#34;&gt;School of
Computer Science &amp;amp; Statistics&lt;/a&gt; at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tcd.ie&#34;&gt;Trinity College
Dublin&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;current-project&#34;&gt;Current Project&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I work on an EU project called &lt;a href=&#34;http://diversify-project.eu&#34;&gt;Diversify&lt;/a&gt; which aims at using &amp;lsquo;Diversity&amp;rsquo; as a foundational principle in making better collaborative adaptive systems. My main interest is in self-adaptive systems, engineering them, predicting/controlling their various properties, getting them to collaborate, and  preventing/boosting emergent effects.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>