<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Scrum on Vivek Nallur</title>
    <link>http://viveknallur.github.io/tags/scrum/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Scrum on Vivek Nallur</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright &amp;#169; by Vivek Nallur</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 25 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://viveknallur.github.io/tags/scrum/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Mini-Project using Scrum</title>
      <link>http://viveknallur.github.io/teaching/project/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://viveknallur.github.io/teaching/project/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;The process of the mini-project, to be developed using the scrum methodology, is
detailed here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;group-selection-and-registration:10be9c81b9315bdc8704629d17642664&#34;&gt;Group Selection and Registration&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All students must form groups and register their group with the faculty. A group
can be formed with 4-6 students. Students are free to form groups of their
choice, with the caveat that one student can only belong to one group
(obviously!). It is the students&amp;rsquo; responsibility to ensure that all members of
the group are willing and able to collaborate with each other, since scrum
demands a high level of self-organization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things to do after group formation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Select a team-leader. This is the person who will be the contact point
between the team and the faculty.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The team-leader sends an email to the faculty, registering the group
(remember to cc your group members)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Select your project, and inform the faculty.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the above steps should be &lt;em&gt;finished&lt;/em&gt; before 14-November-2016&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr/&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;project-selection:10be9c81b9315bdc8704629d17642664&#34;&gt;Project Selection&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are three projects outlined on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://viveknallur.github.io/teaching/project-list&#34;&gt;projects&lt;/a&gt;
page.  As a group, select one of the projects, according to your language and
technology preference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Project selection should be &lt;em&gt;finished&lt;/em&gt; before 14-November-2016. Project
development will start on 14-November-2016, when the client outlines his
detailed requirements. The faculty will act as the client for the duration of
the project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr/&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;project-development:10be9c81b9315bdc8704629d17642664&#34;&gt;Project Development&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Project development will be done using the scrum methodology. This entails
weekly sprint cycles. After the client describes the project requirements, the
team will create a &lt;u&gt;Product Backlog&lt;/u&gt; and a &lt;u&gt;Burn-down Chart&lt;/u&gt;. The
final and weekly deliverables will be given in the detailed project
requirements. To enable weekly sprint cycles, and meetings with the client, some
lectures will be converted to meeting time. Teams can request the client for a
meeting, by booking an &lt;a href=&#34;http://viveknallur.github.io/teaching/client-meetings&#34;&gt;available slot&lt;/a&gt;.  Code must
be committed to the team-leader&amp;rsquo;s repository (same as the one being used for the
assignments), on the &amp;lsquo;project&amp;rsquo; branch, for every weekly sprint cycle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There will be four sprint cycles:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;14-November to 21-November&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;22-November to 28-November&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;29-November to 5-December&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;6-December to 12-December&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sprint deliverables are due the day after the end of the sprint. A list of
sprint deliverables and their schedule can be found
&lt;a href=&#34;http://viveknallur.github.io/teaching/scrum-schedule&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
At the end of the second sprint cycle, a &lt;em&gt;change request&lt;/em&gt; will be initiated by
the client. This will modify the &lt;em&gt;Product Backlog&lt;/em&gt;.
&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The end of the fourth sprint cycle marks the end of the project, and the &lt;em&gt;Final
Deliverables&lt;/em&gt; mentioned in the detailed requirements must be committed to the
team-leader&amp;rsquo;s repository by the end of 13-December, at the latest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr/&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>